15 chapter 16 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna Su chapter 16 The Fire Later on an evening a traveler's
horse was brought in by the second oser and while he was cleaning him a young
man with a pipe in his mouth lounged into the stable to
gossip. “I say Toler said the Osa just run up the ladder into the loft and put some
hay down into this horse's rack would you? only lay down your
pipe.” “All right,” said the other, and went up through the trap door and I heard him
step across the floor overhead and put down the
hay. James came in to look at us the last thing, and then the door was
locked. I cannot say how long I had slept,
nor what time in the night it was, but I woke up very uncomfortable, though I hardly knew
why. I got up; the air seemed all thick and choking. I heard Ginger coughing and
one of the other horses seemed very restless; it was quite dark, and I could
see nothing, but the stable seemed full of smoke, and I hardly knew how to
breathe. The trap door had been left open, and I thought that was the place it came
through. I listened, and heard a soft rushing sort of noise and a low crackling and
snapping. I did not know what it was, but there was something in the sound so
strange that it made me tremble all over. The other horses were all awake;
some were pulling at their halters, others stamping. At last I heard steps outside,
and the oser who had put up the traveler's horse burst into the stable
with a lantern, and began to untie the horses, and try to lead them out; but he
seemed in such a hurry and so frightened himself that he frightened me still more.
The first horse would not go with him; he tried second and third, and they too
would not stir. He came to me next and tried to drag me out of the stall by
force; of course that was no use. He tried us all by turns and then left the
stable. No doubt we were very foolish, but danger seemed to be all round, and there
was nobody we knew to trust in, and always strange and
uncertain. The fresh air that had come in through the open door made it easier to
breathe, but the rushing sound overhead grew louder, and as I looked upward
through the bars of my empty rack I saw a red light flickering on the
wall. Then I heard a cry of “Fire!” outside, and the old Osa quietly and quickly came
in; he got one horse out, and went to another, but the flames were playing
around the trapo and the roaring over overhead was dreadful. The next thing I heard was
James's voice, quiet and cheery, as it always was. “Come, my beauties, it is time
for us to be off, so wake up and come along.” I stood nearest the door, so he
came to me first, patting me as he came in. “Come, Beauty, on with your bridle, my
boy, we'll soon be out of this smother.” It was on in no time; then he
took the scarf off his neck, and tied it lightly over my eyes, and patting and
coaxing he led me out of the stable. Safe in the yard, he slipped the
scarf off my eyes, and shouted, “Here somebody! take this horse while I go back for the
other.” A tall, broad man stepped forward and took me, and James darted back into the
stable. I set up a shrill Winnie as I saw him go. Ginger told me afterward that
Winnie was the best thing I could have done for her, for had she not heard me
outside she would never have had courage to come out. There was much confusion in the yard;
the horses being got out of other stables, and the carriages and gigs being
pulled out of houses and sheds, lest the flames should spread
further. On the other side the yard windows were thrown up, and people were
shouting all sorts of things; but I kept my eye fixed on the stable door, where
the smoke poured out thicker than ever, and I could see flashes of red
light; presently I heard above all the stir and din a loud L clear voice, which
I knew was Masters James Howard! James Howard! Are you
there?” There was no answer, but I heard a crash of something falling in the stable,
and the next moment I gave a loud, joyful nay for I saw James coming through the
smoke leading Ginger with him; she was coughing violently, and he was not able to
speak. “My brave lad!” said master, laying his hand on his shoulder, “are you
hurt?” James shook his head, for he could not yet
speak ah said the big man who held me; “he is a brave lad, and no
mistake.” “And now,” said master, “when you have got your breath, James, we'll get out
of this place as quickly as we can,” and we were moving towards the entry, when
from the marketplace there came a sound of galloping feet and loud rumbling
wheels is the fire engine the fire engine shouted two or three voices, “stand back, make
way!” and clattering and thundering over the stones two horses dashed into the
yard with a heavy engine behind them. The firemen leaped to the ground; there was
no need to ask where the fire was— —it was rolling up in a great blaze from the
roof. We got out as fast as we could into the broad quiet Marketplace the stars
were shining, and except the noise behind us, all was still. Master led the way to a large
hotel on the other side, and as soon as the Osa came, he said, “James, I must now
hasten to your mistress; I trust the horses entirely to you, order whatever
you think is needed,” and with that he was gone. The master did not run, but I never
saw a mortal man walk so fast as he did that night. There was a dreadful sound before
we got into our stalls— —the shrieks of those poor horses that were left burning
to death in the stable— —it was very terrible! and made both Ginger and me
feel very bad. We, however, were taken in and well done
by. The next morning the master came to see how we were and to speak to James. I
did not hear much, for the Osa was rubbing me down, but I could see that
James looked very happy, and I thought the master was proud of him. Our mistress
had been so much alarmed in the night that the journey was put off till the
afternoon, so James had the morning on hand, and went first to the inn to see
about our harness and the carriage, and then to hear more about the
fire. When he came back we heard him tell the oser about it. At first no one could
guess how the fire had been caused, but at last a man said he saw Dick Towler go
into the stable with a pipe in his mouth,
and when he came out he had not one, and went to the tap for another.
Then the under oler said that he had asked Dick to go up the ladder to put
down some hay, but told him to lay down his pipe first. Dick denied taking the pipe with
him, but no one believed him. I remember our John Manley's rule, never to allow a
pipe in the stable, and thought it ought to be the rule
everywhere. James said the roof and floor had all fallen in, and that only the
black walls were standing; the two poor horses that could not be got out were
buried under the burnt rafters and
tiles end of chapter